So actually we bow
to innocence within us.
And this innocence is the one
gives you the enlightenment.
As I told you yesterday,
the light has innocence.
But this is innocent without knowledge.
But your light is innocent
with knowledge.
We always think that the people who have
got knowledge can never be innocent,
can never be simple.
And the idea we have got about innocence is
that an innocent person is always deceived,
can be befooled, and
can be always taken for granted.
But innocence is a power.
It is a power which protects you,
which gives you light of knowledge.
Knowledge that we have in the worldly
sense is how to exploit others,
how to cheat others, how to make money
out of them,
how to make fun of others,
how to look down upon others.
But the light of innocence is the light
by which you know that
love is the highest thing.
And it teaches you how to love others,
how to care for others,
how to be gentle about others.
It also gives you the light within.
It's just the other way round of this
avidya that we have in this world.
Just the other way round.
The avidya outside teaches us competition,
how to put the other person down,
because it has fear.
It is insecured.
This knowledge is not secure at all.
If it had security it would not
have behaved like this.
But the light of innocence knows everything.
It has no fear.
When we say children are innocent,
we mean to say that they have
that power of innocence.
Many times people have noticed
if a child falls from a height
he doesn't die, while a young man
may die with a much smaller height.
And the child is not afraid while falling.
He just enjoys as if there's
a parachute coming down nicely.
And then when he falls down also, just
gets up, laughs, smiles at everyone.
He doesn't understand
why everybody is worried.
Because in that innocence he knows
that he's looked after.
He's protected.
He knows that there is a power which
is much higher than him,
and he does not have to worry.
Then we start putting ideas into
the head of the child,
and that is how he starts losing
his power of innocence
and he becomes a coward.
He becomes a cunning fellow.
He becomes an unrighteous personality.
But still we would say that the
innocence of children
is innocence of ignorance
in a way,
because they do not know the
dangers of life.
But the light of innocence knows
all the dangers,
and also knows how to get rid of it.
Also knows how to be away from
such a question.
There was a wise man who was
going on a staircase.
And there was a stupid man coming from
the other side. Foolish man.
So foolish people are always aggressive,
that is one of the signs,
because they have inferiority complex.
So the foolish man says to the
man who was coming up,
he says — one had to move on one side —
so he says, "I don't move for fools."
The foolish one says.
So the wise man says, "I do,"
and he moved.
That's how the light of innocence
tells you how far to go with a person,
how far to talk to a person,
how far to indulge in another person's
personality or his problems.
Otherwise he recedes.
He understands that this gentleman
is a stupid fool,
so I move for a fool like that.
He doesn't pay attention
to such a person.
He doesn't bother about such a person.
This is the light of innocence which
gives you discrimination —
how far to go with others.